If you want better local SEO results,
you need to win on Google, but in 2026,
you can't ignore other platforms that
influence visibility. That's why the
real play now is search everywhere
optimization. My name's Nathan Gotch and
I've led hundreds of successful SEO and
local SEO campaigns since 2013 and my
systems are used by thousands of SEO
professionals and agencies worldwide.
Let's get right into it. I'm going to be
building a local SEO strategy from
scratch in less than 30 minutes. So, I
picked a random business in Ballwin,
Missouri. Right away when we look at
this particular Google Business Profile,
it's got some good stuff going for it,
but it has some There's a glaring
opportunity that we're looking at right
here. As you can tell, they service the
city of Ballwin, but when we look at
their preferred location, they're
actually preferring Chesterfield. This
is a big mistake and you can see their
address is actually in Ballwin. Like
they They are situated in the city of
Ballwin, but yet the Google Business
Profile is optimized for Chesterfield.
So, this is is simple as literally going
to the Google Business Profile, just
switching it to Ballwin, and boom,
performance will probably jump five five
to seven spots in the Google Business
Profile in the local pack. And plus,
they have a lot of reviews, right?
Nearly 700 reviews. So, just a simple
switch on that can just like immediately
improve their performance. Aside from
that, everything else looks pretty
solid. I think they could add maybe more
visual depth and enhance the profile a
little bit, but at the end of the day,
just make sure you're targeting Ballwin
and that's going to do most of the heavy
lifting there in the Google Business
Profile and continue to drive reviews
consistently. Now, going back to that,
whenever you start one of these
campaigns, what you don't want to do is
start taking action right away. If you
see something you're like, "Oh, I'm just
going to go fix this right away." I
would hold off on doing that, especially
if you're working with Let's say this
was my client. It's smart to go and get
a benchmark report. Go and benchmark the
information and the performance before
you start acting, so at least you can
see the performance gains over time. So,
what I do is I set up tracking and you'd
go into your preferred tracking
software, but the key thing here is no
matter what you're tracking, you have to
track multiple surfaces, multiple search
surfaces, especially for local. The
first one that matters the most is the
local pack, okay? So, you can see here
we're tracking dentists in Ballwin,
Missouri, okay? So, they're number 20
for dentist Ballwin, Missouri. They
literally have a location in Ballwin and
they're still losing dramatically. And
they're actually have more reviews than
a lot of the top competitors. That
location switch,
I hate to use the word guarantee when it
comes to SEO, but I've just seen this so
many times and how effective this will
be.
Changing a location to the correct
location or changing a category to the
correct category, sometimes you can see
a lift of five, sometimes even 10 spots
just for 1 second of work, okay? So, I'm
telling you if they just change this,
boom, they're going to pop up probably
top 10 at least in the local pack, okay?
And then they've got to keep chipping
away there. But that's a very simple
thing and then you can even see in the
grid here, it's causing a lot of
problems for them because they've
optimized for Chesterfield, so they're
just not doing really well in the
location that they're actually
servicing. And then aside from that,
we'll go and check their category. So,
they got the right category, dentist, so
they're good to go on that, all right?
Now, in addition to the local pack, we
know that to influence local pack, we
are going to focus just on the Google
Business Profile, right? That's one of
the key things. Now, there's a bunch of
other secondary variables that we should
consider outside of the Google Business
Profile, but we'll talk about here in a
second. But we also want to be tracking
traditional search, right? How are they
doing in traditional search? And we see
here
there's opportunity, right? Like they
they have competitors that are beating
them across multiple search engines
and they're doing okay, but there's room
to improve and I'll show you some of the
gaps that exist in the traditional
search results. But remember, on the
local level, you really want to be
thinking about just dominating the first
page and trying to occupy as much serp
real estate as you possibly can. So, you
want to hit that local pack, you want to
rank in the traditional search results,
you also want to rank on other websites
in the search results as well, not just
your website. We'll talk about that here
in a second.
And then the AI answers, okay? This is
absolutely critical. If you've been
doing SEO the way you should be over the
last two to three years, you should be
thinking about your brand or your
client's visibility inside of AI
answers. So, you can see here, they're
actually doing really well. They're
visible across four different AI
platforms. They're not visible across
ChatGPT, which is the one that really
matters the most here, but you can see
they're doing quite well, right? Like
Gemini, Perplexity, Claude, Grok.
They're doing well, all right? There's
room to improve, but they're doing
pretty well and that's a good sign, all
right? Then we also want to see AI
citations, all right? This is a big one
here because first of all, we want to be
one of the cited sources. So, you want
to try to your own website, try to be
one of those citation sources, one of
those sources of retrieval, but we also
want to be looking at the opportunities,
okay? What opportunities exist here?
Now, some of these are competitors, but
some of them are not. We have
Healthgrades and then we also have Delta
Dental. So, these are two obvious
citation opportunities that we're going
to want to pursue. Now, I'm going to
show you how to take this to the next
level, okay? Now, actually before I get
to that, make sure you have Google
Search Console installed and make sure
you have Google Analytics 4 installed
and make sure you have call tracking,
okay? Those are the three additional
tracking things that you need to do for
local. This is pretty much all you need.
You need to be tracking across all of
these search surfaces and you can see
like just with some slight tweaks to the
things I'm going to be showing here in a
second, can see dramatic lifts in
visibility here. Now, the one thing I
really want to show you is the citation
sources. So, for many years, you would
on the local level, we would just go and
build citations and it'd be like a
one-and-done activity. Like, let's go
build our citations and then move on to
some other stuff because honestly, they
weren't that important. But they have
become important again and but not in
the way that you think. So, this is not
a game of volume. The way you want to
think about citations is simply just to
look at what citations are popping up in
for this particular industry, this
niche, this particular scenario, okay?
And then those are your You should put
all your focus and all your energy on
those because we know that they're being
used in the AI platforms. So, from
there, it becomes quite simple. So, like
in in this case,
you're only got about three, right? We
got Healthgrades, we got Delta Dental,
and we've got Yelp, all right? So, we've
got basically three citation sources
that we need to get hyper-focused on and
do a really good job there. And also
ada.org as well. So, we actually got
four, okay? So, four total citation
sources. Based on most local industries
that we've seen, four to seven, give or
take, citations that you're going to
spend your time on. The rest are
probably not worth your time at all,
okay? So, what does that mean though to
spend your time here? You want to be
thinking about how do we actually do SEO
on this citation source, okay? So, when
we're looking at Healthgrades, how do I
actually get this particular dentist to
show up higher on this particular
directory, okay? And so, when we're
looking at this, clearly we've got 1 2
3, we've got three sponsored listings
here.
Maybe worth considering being a
sponsored listing. Here's the thing, the
AI platforms don't care if it's
sponsored or not. So, it's going to come
in here and it's going to see these
three brands popping up here and it's
going to give it weight just because
it's here, just because it's the the
most retrievable and then also improve
the organic performance in this list,
okay? And we can see the particular
dentist that we're looking at here,
they're not actually showing up anywhere
super high on this list. They're all the
way down here. So, the question is what
should Brandon in this case do? He needs
to go to his profile
and he needs to start driving reviews to
this profile, okay? Start driving
reviews here. This is what I would call
a secondary review surface where Google
is 90% of your effort for your reviews,
the other 10% should be going to these
secondary citation sources as a way to
ultimately improve the visibility in AI
platforms, okay? So, start with the
reviews. The next thing is just looking
at the profile itself. It's very thin,
right? When we look at this stuff,
not a lot of information. You've got a
couple of reviews in there, but it's
pretty, pretty light. So, we need to
actually optimize this profile just like
we would a webpage on our own website.
Very simply, run it through a content
optimization tool, okay? So, I did an
extraction of this particular profile
just to show you this and you can see
like it's pulling a bunch of stuff
that's not relevant to him, which
naturally would happen on a
directory-based website. But if you were
to get rid of all this other fluff
stuff, you'd basically be left with a
sentence about what he does, right?
Okay? So, what this tells me is I would
want to re-optimize
this particular profile. And so, you
could just regenerate the draft and it's
going to use all of these keyword
opportunities to build something
incredibly relevant, right? And we're
looking at a target of maybe 500 words.
This will vary depending on the type of
platform that you're using. We don't
know the restrictions as far as how deep
you can go on content on Healthgrades,
but you can still use that original
asset that's been generated by the AI
and then you can even take it and throw
it into ChatGPT and say, "Okay, I need
you to compress this down to 150 words
or 300 words." Whatever the limitation
is, but this will greatly improve
performance on this particular profile.
It may actually allow you to even maybe
even rank this profile in traditional
search, right? That's a secondary thing
that you can do to occupy more real
estate. So, that's what you should be
thinking about is I need to actually
optimize my profiles, right? So, you
optimize your website, then you optimize
your profiles. And you can see
in about couple seconds here, we can
already see great improvement as far as
covering the appropriate topics much
better, by a lot quicker, a lot better.
Like dental veneers, you just click on
this and it will the AI will find a
place to cover that topic in a natural
way. And you can see, perfectly covers
that topic, no problem at all. So, this
is just what you can do. You keep adding
more and more to make it more relevant
and you repeat this process for all your
critical profiles. Next thing we're
going to be doing here is we're going to
focus on the brand itself. Come here,
and I'm going to show you two different
techniques.
The first technique is using Chat GPT,
and this is a prompt that you can use.
And basically, what it's going to do is
it's going to it's going to scour the
internet and look for inconsistencies
about this brand. Okay, that's what you
want to identify those inconsistencies
and then go and attack them. And so, you
can see here, I just used GPT 5.4 to do
this, but regardless, you have two
options here. You can use GPT 5.4
thinking, and you'll still get a really
comprehensive analysis. And you can see
this apparently this practice was taken
over by the current dentist. So, it
actually made a it transitioned, and
there's a bunch of old baggage left over
from the previous dentist still floating
around the internet. So, this is
something you want to go and start
cleaning up and and improving all of the
accuracy for this particular dental
practice or any business that you're
working on, okay? And this is just
barely any work to do, but you get a
massive report, tons of work that you
can execute on. You can also use deep
research, okay? Honestly, I've been I
haven't really been using deep research
as much as I used to because I have
found that
5.4 or even 5.2 prior to this,
it uses web search anyway, and it does
pretty much the same thing, and it takes
way less time. So, I would just my
preference is I just use the 5.4
thinking, and I let it just run, and
it's way quicker, okay?
So, that's what you do. Then now, we're
going to move into technical SEO, okay?
So, from here, I'm just doing a very
simple Screaming Frog crawl. If I had
access to Google Analytics and Google
Search Console, I would integrate those
as well, okay?
But in this case, I don't. So, couple
key things we're looking at here. This
site is actually not in that bad of
shape. There's just some kind of broader
level things that we need to go after.
So, the first one is is title tag
optimization is quite aggressive, okay?
I would not be this aggressive with
title tags.
And you can see right here, for example,
we have dental bonding in Ballwin,
Missouri, which is great. This is a fine
title tag. But then we've got dental
bonding plus the zip code, and now we're
just getting over optimized. So, you
would just get rid of this and just keep
it like this, all right? And this would
be totally fine. This would work
perfectly well, okay? That should be the
style. You could even just use the the
actual dentist name here. So, you know,
like Brandon Cousins, DDS, you know,
maybe if you don't want to use the
dental practice name, it could just be
like this. But either way, you don't
need to include the secondary variations
in here plus a zip code because LLMs are
incredibly smart, and they know those
are the same thing. So, you do not need
to do that, and it will not actually
improve your performance. It actually
probably hurt you more than anything.
And then meta description, when we look
at this, couple key things here. We got
the boilerplate meta descriptions here.
Now that we have LLMs, there's just no
good reason not to have unique meta
descriptions like every single
description you write can be unique now
with barely any effort. So, I would
highly recommend rewriting every meta
description. Make sure it's unique. I
don't recommend putting the phone number
in the meta description. The reason is
because organic CTR is critical, and we
know it's a proven ranking factor. So,
when you put that phone number in there,
you're greatly increasing the odds that
someone is not going to click. We need
them to click. That is absolutely
critical. So, I would avoid putting the
phone number in the title or the meta
description. This does not apply to the
Google Business Profile. I'm just purely
talking about your traditional search
results, okay? So, you I would be
careful doing that. And then aside from
that, I think everything else is pretty
solid. The only thing I would avoid
doing is like this informational stuff.
This is not the type of content you want
to be creating on the local level. This
is all just generic stuff that AI can
easily produce.
How long do dental implants last? Okay,
that's a general question on the
national level. It's not going to serve
this website that only focuses on
Ballwin. So, you want to focus just on
your core location. Don't focus on
topics that are generally
in the practice itself. That's not a
good idea. You want to focus
specifically on the location and the
subject matter expertise that you're
going after. So, how do you do that?
Very easy. Go into Chat GPT, and I'll
run a couple examples. So, the first one
here is link bait, okay? So, you can run
this prompt
and come up with different
statistics-driven ideas. It's like
endless amounts of ideas that you can
run. There's no shortage of ideas. Yeah,
you come up with the ideas, then you
just need to go and execute these. Some
of them are good, some are not, but the
point is you can see this is much better
because it's focused specifically on
Ballwin, and that is the key. We want to
build that proper relevance and
localized relevance for this site. Then
we go down, we can run the same thing
here, similar concept, and you can see
these are additional local content ideas
as well. So, once again, just use these
prompts and just make them applicable to
any business that you're currently
working on, okay? And then we can
actually go over here, and this is the
last piece of this equation,
which is some additional offsite work.
So, with one simple one-shot prompt like
this, you can basically be done with all
of your link prospecting, okay? You can
see right here within about took about 4
minutes, we've got all kinds of link
prospects that we can pursue
specifically in Ballwin, okay? And this
will help us build proper topic
relevance and topic authority the way
that we really should be doing it, okay?
And then the last piece of this is the
page level as well. So, when we I showed
you the the different dedicated pages
here. So, they have Invisalign in
Ballwin, Missouri. This is actually a
proper structure. I think this is
actually good right here. So, we have
the service, then we have the core
location. This is actually a very good
setup. I would stick to doing this.
That's good. But it's really about the
optimization of those pages. So, you can
see here like this is the homepage, and
it has probably too many words, a little
aggressive. It's not actually optimized
particularly well. And so, you'd really
want something more like this, right?
Which is like you've got a word count
that's more within range of the
competitors than that median word count
range, and then you are properly
covering all of the critical topics and
entities, okay? That's what a good page
is going to look like for SEO purposes.
It's going to be perfectly optimized for
the location and that primary topic,
okay? And you can see this is for
cosmetic dentists in Ballwin, Missouri.
Took about 3 minutes to build this,
okay?
And then you can just literally go in
here and export whatever CMS you're
using. You can literally just click this
HTML, hand this off to the AI, and boom,
it will go and just format this exactly
how you want. And of course, you'll need
to design it and work on that. But you
can do it that way. You can also go and
just export a classic markdown file.
Once again, very useful for AI
platforms. They understand markdown
exceptionally well. And if you're using
WordPress, obviously, you're going to
have to work with whatever builder you
have. So,
that is a full local SEO strategy in
less than 30 minutes. Told you I would
do it. So, that's Those are all the kind
of component pieces you need to go
through. You get your tracking set up.
You attack the core citations that tend
to show up, right? We want to go and we
can continue to acquire links around the
local area to build localized
topic authority.
And then we need to just fill in all the
topic gaps. So, focus on your service
pages first, and you build relevant
content for all of your service pages,
cosmetic dentists, and all your
secondary services. Do that first. Then
once you've got all those knocked out,
then just move into building topic
support with proper informational
content or informational assets that
focus on the local area. As I
demonstrated, these are the types of
assets we want to be building
specifically to support this brand.